<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-21T20:17:59+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Home</title><subtitle>Agneesh Barua's website with information on latest research and publications.</subtitle><author><name>Agneesh Barua</name></author><entry><title type="html">Metavenom paper published</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/meatavenom_pblished_post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metavenom paper published" /><published>2019-04-19T04:34:30+09:00</published><updated>2019-04-19T04:34:30+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/meatavenom_pblished_post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/meatavenom_pblished_post.html">&lt;p&gt;The metavenom paper is published in &lt;a href=&quot;hhttps://www.pnas.org/content/118/14/e2021311118/tab-article-info&quot;&gt;PNAS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/pnas_cover.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; class=&quot;align-left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper we talk about how a conserved gene regulatory network lead to rise of oral venom in tetrapods.
Most studies focus on the toxins to understand the evolution of the snake venom phenotype, but here we took a different approach and looked at all the genes that co-express with snake venom. We found a network of co-expressed genes (the metavenom) to be highly enriched for processes involved in protein folding and maintaining cellular homeostasis during protein expression. This makes perfect sense since the venom tissue has a high protein load, it needs to ensure the molecular machinery that can maintain this protein load is actively present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also show that there is substantial conservation of the metavenom in salivary tissue of mammals, suggesting that this network was likely already present in the common ancestor of reptiles and mammals. This was fascinating because it means that although reptiles and mammals have taken different directions in their use of oral secretions, the common building blocks are the same. This could also help explain how oral venoms can seemingly evolve independently in so many disparate lineages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next steps are writing up a paper on the evolution of serine protease based venoms that seem to suggest that the most abundant venom component in mammals and reptiles actually evolved in parallel from the same ancestral gene, and not independently as previously believed. This, added with our metavenom work really blurs the line between what we think are venomous and how we should append the way we classify venomous animals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Agneesh Barua</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">The metavenom paper is published in PNAS.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Metavenom paper is a huge success</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/meatavenom_sucess.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Metavenom paper is a huge success" /><published>2019-04-19T04:34:30+09:00</published><updated>2019-04-19T04:34:30+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/meatavenom_sucess</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/meatavenom_sucess.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/118/14/e2021311118/tab-article-info&quot;&gt;metavenom&lt;/a&gt; paper has garnered a lot of attention!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an Altmetric of over 1600, the metavenom paper now stands in the 99th percentile of all research Altmetric has ever tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/meta-altmetric.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conservation of the metavenom between mammals and snakes has lead to many sensationalised headlines on how humans can one day become venomous. While highly unlikely, the fact that many molecular components are shared between mammals and reptiles does call for further investigation into the origins of specialisations from common building blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few more nuanced articles are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/could-humans-be-venomous.html&quot;&gt;Live Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://theprint.in/science/scientists-find-first-direct-evidence-that-venom-glands-evolved-from-salivary-glands/631760/&quot;&gt;The Print&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oist.jp/news-center/press-releases/mouse%E2%80%99s-bite-holds-venomous-potential-finds-new-study&quot;&gt;OIST press release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another highlight was a recommendation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://facultyopinions.com/prime/739835180?utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_source=prime_follow_faculty#eval793584962&quot;&gt;Faculty Opinions&lt;/a&gt; by Rafael Zardoya, Diego San Mauro, and Iker Irisarri. They described our approach as &lt;strong&gt;“novel and elegant.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most valuable mention of our research was when the &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution.berkeley.edu/evolibrary/news/210408_evovenom&quot;&gt;Understanding Evolution Blog&lt;/a&gt; from Berekely used our paper as a resource to teach convergence and homology. This was special for me because, as an undergrad, I used to read these blogs pretty often and was a source of inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Agneesh Barua</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">The metavenom paper has garnered a lot of attention!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Serine protease preprint up</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/SP_post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Serine protease preprint up" /><published>2019-04-19T04:34:30+09:00</published><updated>2019-04-19T04:34:30+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/SP_post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/04/19/SP_post.html">&lt;p&gt;The serine protease preprint is up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.08.06.240747v1&quot;&gt;biorxiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study tried to trace the evolution of one of the most ubiquitous venom components across animals, the serine protease (SP) based venoms. Both mammals and reptiles actively use SP toxins in their venom. However, it was believed that these components evolved independently in both lineages. Following the revelation of a conserved gene regulatory network behind oral secretions, we wondered if the toxins could also be conserved or have a common origin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/sp_fig.png&quot; alt=&quot;image&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found that SP-based toxins in reptiles and mammals descended from a single ancient gene that shares its ancestor with fish anionic trypsins. This new result will change a decades-long misconception that constraint and convergence lead to the rise of similar toxins across lineages. Instead, we show that parallel evolution from a common ancestor is likely to be a good source of adaptive novelty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned to this space to find out more….&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Agneesh Barua</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="Jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">The serine protease preprint is up on biorxiv.</summary></entry></feed>